Andrew Ellicott Douglass papers, 1867-1962
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Andrew Ellicott Douglass papers, 1867-1962
AZ 072
Douglass, A. E. (Andrew Ellicott), 1867-1962
Chiefly materials related to A.E. Douglass' astronomical and tree-ring research, and administration, at the Harvard College Observatory, Lowell Observatories, Steward Observatory, Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research, and University of Arizona. Includes correspondence, photographs, and an unpublished biography.
90 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL:http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
Several items have been restricted. Please see the container list for more details.
Biographical Note
American astronomer and educator, founder of the science of dendrochronology. Associated with the Harvard College Observatory, 1889-1894, and its expedition to Peru; as well as the Lowell Observatories in Flagstaff, Arizona, 1894-1901, and Mexico, 1896-1897. At the University of Arizona, Tucson, 1906-1962; served as professor, dean and acting president, first director of the Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research, and also the Steward Observatory.
Organization
This collection is organized into five series:
Series I: Personal Material (Part I), 1867-1962
Series II: Astronomy Materials, 1890-1965
Series III: University of Arizona, 1904-1962
Series IV: Tree-Ring Material, 1894-1966
Series V: Personal Material (Part II), 1867-1965
Scope and Content Note
Chiefly materials related to A.E. Douglass' astronomical and tree-ring research, and administraiton, at the Harvard College Observatory, Lowell Observatories, Steward Observatory, Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research, and University of Arizona. Includes scientific records; clippings; photographs of astronomical images, observatories, and tree-rings; typescripts of speeches and manuscripts; his published articles; reprints of articles by others; and lecture notes. Correspondence with other scientists includes William Henry Pickering, Percival Lowell, Godfrey Sykes, and Edmund Schulman. Personal correspondence is with his wife Ida Whittington Douglass, and other family members and friends. Drafts, proofs, and final editions, (1919-1936) from of his book Climatic Cycles and Tree Growth.
Involvement with scientific organizations such as the Carnegie Institution, 1918-1938, and the Aemrican Associatiuon for the Advancement of Science, 1919-1950, is documented; as are his scholarly contributions to conferences. Personal items cover his childhood and his student days at Trinity College, Hartford, 1885-1889; travels to other countries; and participation in numerous civic and Masonic groups. An unpublished biography of Douglass by David Brinegar is present. Photographs, mainly black-and-white, some cyanotype, depict professional and social activities, personal life, and travels. The South American photographs from the 1890s include Incla ruins in Bolivia, topical views of Chile, and the Harvard College Observatory in Arequipa, Peru.
Lowell, Percival, 1855-1916 -- Correspondence; Schulman, Edmund, 1908-1958 -- Correspondence; Sykes, Godfrey, 1861-1948 -- Correspondence; Pickering, William H. (William Henry), 1858- -- Correspondence; American Association for the Advancement of Science -- Southwestern and Rocky Mountain Division; Lowell Observatory -- History -- Sources; Harvard College Observatory -- History -- Sources; Steward Observatory -- History -- Sources; Trinity College (Hartford, Conn.) -- History -- Sources; University of Arizona -- Faculty; University of Arizona -- Laboratory of Tree-Ring Research; University of Arizona -- Administration -- History -- Sources; Carnegie Institution of Washington; Scientific apparatus and instruments; Scientists -- Arizona; Astronomical observatories -- Arizona; Astronomical observatories -- Mexico; Astronomical observatories -- Peru; Climatology -- Research; Dendrochronology -- Research; Solar eclipses -- Observations; Tree-rings -- Research; Solar energy -- Research; Sunspots -- Research; Weather forecasting -- Research; South America -- Description and travel -- Photographs; Correspondence; Diaries; Photographs; Slides
Separated Material
Some publications, maps, and photographs were removed from this collection and cataloged separately.
Container List
- Series I: Personal Material (Part I), 1867-1962
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: Ellicott Family. 1871 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: Andrew Ellicott (miscellaneous). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: George Washington Letter to Andrew Ellicott (photocopy, original in possession of the family of A.E. Douglass). October 20, 1792 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: Ellicott Instrumenst and Journal (correspondence). 1902-1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: Ellicott Instrument (photographs). (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: Douglass Genealogy (correspondence). (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: David Bates Douglass (correspondence). (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ellicott & Douglass Families: Mathews, Catharine Van Cortlandt: Andrew Ellicott: His Life and Letters. 1908 (Box 1)
  - Childhood: correspondence (family). 1871-1880 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Childhood: correspondence (friends, relatives). 1867-1880 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Childhood: Central Grammar School (report cards, compositions, drawings, and "examinations on the blackboard"). 1867-1880 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Childhood: diaries and miscellaneous items. 1876, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Childhood: photographs (A.E.D. and childhood surroundings). 1867-1880 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Childhood: valentines. 1867-1880 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Childhood: Ward, The Telescope. 3rd edition. Inscribed, "Andrew Ellicott Douglass. A Birthday present from his loving father. July 5, 1878." 1869 (Box 2)
  - Childhood: scrapbook kept by A.E.D. as a child. 1867-1880 (Box 2)
  - Punchard Free School: correspondence (family & friends). 1881-1884 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Punchard Free School: correspondence (Prosser H. Frye, classmate). 1884-1885 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Punchard Free School: A.E.D.'s compositions. 1881-1884 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Punchard Free School: miscellaneous items. 1881-1884 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Punchard Free School: The Punchard Ensign (volumes one and four). 1881-1885 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Punchard Free School: photographs (A.E.D., classmates, teachers). 1881-1884 (Box 3)
  - Punchard Free School: notebook. May 16, 1881-1882 (Box 3)
  - Punchard Free School: diary. 1884 (Box 3)
  - Punchard Free School: small box, "Lenses of my youth, including some I ground about 1881." 1881-1884 (Box 3)
  - Youthful Inventions & Drawing Instruments: 3 telephone receivers. (Box 4)
  - Youthful Inventions & Drawing Instruments: 1 tube for spectroscope. 1882-1883 (Box 4)
  - Youthful Inventions & Drawing Instruments: 4 small cases of drawing instruments. (Box 4)
  - Youthful Inventions & Drawing Instruments: 1 small fan scale. (Box 4)
  - Trinity College: diaries. 1886-1889 (Box 5)
  - Trinity College: miscellaneous items. 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Trinity College: photographs (A.E.D.--individual photos & with groups). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Trinity College: photographs (buildings and views of Trinity). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Trinity College: photographs (classmates). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Trinity College: photographs (scientific, astronomica, trick photography). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Trinity College: photographs (Scudder Benefit). 1888 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Trinity College: photographs (student rooms). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Trinity College: photographs (Blizzard of 1888; Collapse of Hotel 1889; Storm, Plymouth Wharf, 1886). 1886-1889 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Trinity College: photographs (family & friends). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Trinity College: photographs (East Wareham, "camp"). 1885-1889 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (Mother). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (Mother). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (Father). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (brother, Benjamin H. Douglass). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (brother, David B. Douglass). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (brother, Malcolm Douglass). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (sister, Mary Caroline Douglass). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (brother, Moses H. Douglass). 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Trinity College: miscellaneous correspondence, clippings, etc. 1885-1889 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (friends & relatives). 1885-1888 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (friends & relatives). 1885-1888 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (Flavel S. Luther, President of Trinity College). 1885-1889 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Trinity College: photographs and clippings (Flavel S. Luther). 1885-1889 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (classmate, Prosser H. Frye). 1886-1934 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (with Trinity College officials after graduation). 1944-1958 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (with Trinity College officials after graduation). 1944-1958 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (with various classmates after graduation). (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (R. McClelland Brady, classmate). 1924-1949 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Trinity College: correspondence (R. McClelland Brady, classmate). 1950-1955 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Trinity College: Psi Upsilon Fraternity. 1912-1958 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Trinity College: The Tenth General Catalogue of the Psi Upsilon Fraternity. Published under the direction of the Executive Council, in the 55th year of the fraternity. March 1888 (Box 8)
  - Trinity College: The Diamond of Psi Upsilon, volume 17, no. 1. November 1930 (Box 8)
  - Trinity College: A.E.D. and Spiritualism (reports of seances, etc). 1885-1889 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Trinity College: photography notes. 1889 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Trinity College: various compositions. 1885-1889 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Trinity College: physics notes. 1885-1889 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Trinity College: scientific notes & observations; geometry problems, miscellanous astronomical observations and drawings. 1885-1889 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Trinity College: brochures, pictures, etc. 1909-1950 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Trinity College: publications in which A.E.D. is mentioned. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Trinity College: The Trinity Ivy yearbook, volumes 16 & 17. 1888-1889 (Box 9)
  - Trinity College: Catalogus Senatus Academici Collegii Sanctissimae Trinitatis. 1900 (Box 9)
  - Trinity College: mailing list. April 1901 (Box 9)
  - Trinity College: Addresses of former graduates, former students, and recipients of honorary degrees. May 1903 (Box 9)
  - Trinity College: T rinity College Bulletin: Living Alumni. April 1918 (Box 9)
  - Trinity College: Trinity College Bulletin: Alumni Directory. January 1956 (Box 9)
  - South America: A.E.D.'s letters to family. 1891-1893 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - South America: A.E.D.'s letters regarding trip to La Paz. April 1891 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - South America: letters to family to A.E.D. 1890-1893 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - South America: Boston and Harvard University Mementos. 1890-1893 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - South America: diaries and notebooks. 1890-1893 (Box 10)
  - South America: photographs (A.E.D.). 1890-1893 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - South America: photographs (friends and associates). 1890-1893 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - South America: photographs (Harvard College Observatory, Arequipa, Peru). 1890-1893 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - South America: photographs (Bolivia). 1890-1893 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - South America: photographs (Chile). 1890-1893 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - South America: photographs (Peru). 1890-1893 (Box 11A, Folder 1)
  - South America: photographs (Arequipa, Peru). 1890-1893 (Box 11A, Folder 2)
  - South America: photographs (Chachani, Peru & Harvard College Observatory Meteorological Shelter). 1890-1893 (Box 11A, Folder 3)
  - South America: photographs (unidentified). 1890-1893 (Box 11A, Folder 4)
  - South America: "Bolivian Geographical Work." 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - South America: "A Mountain Climb in Peru." 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - South America: "Indications of a Rainy Period in Southern Peru," Science, vol.20, no.507. October 21, 1892 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - South America: "The Crescentic Dunes of Peru," Appalachia, vol.12, no.1. July 1909 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - South America: "Work on Swift's Comet," Astronomy and Astro-Physics. June 1894 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - South America: miscellaneous work relating to the 2nd Peruvian Expedition. 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - South America: miscellaneous work to be prepared for publication. 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - South America: correspondence (general). 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - South America: observations and records (various). 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - South America: miscellaneous. 1890-1893 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - South America: "South America" (lecture). 1948 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - South America: Triangulation Book no.1. 1890-1893 (Box 13)
  - South America: Triangulation Book no.2. 1890-1893 (Box 13)
  - South America: Triangulation Book no.3. 1890-1893 (Box 13)
  - South America: El Valle De Arequipa, by Jorge Polar. 189? (Box 13)
  - South America: Bradley's Pocket Map of South America, northern sheet. 1887 (Box 13)
  - South America: Rand, McNally & Co.'s South America. March 18, 1890 (Box 13)
  - South America: various publications relating to South Aemrican trip. 1890-1893 (Box 13)
  - Pickering Family: correspondence (William H. Pickering). 1889-1912 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Pickering Family: correspondence (William H. Pickering). 1913-1917 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Pickering Family: correspondence (William H. Pickering). 1918-1922 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Pickering Family: correspondence (William H. Pickering). 1923-1938 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Pickering Family: correspondence (Edward Charles Pickering). 1892-1918 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Pickering Family: correspondence (W.T. Pickering). 1908-1947 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Pickering Family: clippings, photographs, biographical sketches. (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Pickering Family: Observatory in Jamaica.. (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - William H. Pickering, reprints. (Box 15)
- Series II: Astronomy Materials, 1890-1965
  - Lowell Observatory: "Lowelliana." 1894-1901 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Lowell Observatory: clippings and articles. 1894-1903 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Lowell Observatory: clippings and articles. 1894-1960 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Lowell Observatory: miscellaneous papers. 1894-1901 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Lowell Observatory: publications of Percival Lowell. 1894-1901 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Lowell Observatory: "Mars: the Flagstaff Photographs," by Percival Lowell. August 1895 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Lowell Observatory: Diary. 1900-1901 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Lowell Observatory: "The Message from Mars." (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Lowell Observatory: various articles by A.E.D. about Lowell Observatory. 1895,1920,1944 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Lowell Observatory: publications while at Lowell Observatory. 1894-1896 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Lowell Observatory: publications while at Lowell Observatory. 1897-1900 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Lowell Observatory: unpublished work done at Lowell Observatory. 1894-1901 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Lowell Observatory: Luminous Cloud (correspondence). 1896-1897 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Lowell Observatory: scales of seeing. 1894-1901 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Lowell Observatory: clippings relating to astronomy. 1897-1906 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Lowell Observatory: Mars (observations and drawings) after leaving Lowell Observatory. 1903, 1907 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): A.E.D. and Lowell Observatory Personnel. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Exterior. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Interior. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Various Astronomical Photographs. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Zodiacal Light. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Observatory sites. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Photography notes & records, engraving process. 1894-1901 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Lowell Observatory (Photographs): Spectroscope. 1901 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): A.E.D.'s work. 1894-1901 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Artificial Planets. 1898-1901 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Atmospheric Currents. 1895-1904 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Gegenschein observations & records. 1894-1901 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Record book. 1897-1899 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Mars. 1894-1902 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Miscellaneous observations & records. 1896-1901 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Saturn & Satellites. 1897-1900 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): Zodiacal Light. 1891-1899 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Lowell Observatory (Astronomical Observations & Records): trips. 1899-1900 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Annals of the Lowell Observatory, vol. 1 (contains observations of the planet Mars during the opposition of 1894-1895 made at Flagstaff, AZ). 1895 (Box 20a)
  - Annals of the Lowell Observatory, vol. 2 (contains observations of the planet Jupiter and its satellites, and observations of Mars). 1894-1895, 1896-1897 (Box 20b)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: clippings, photographs, diary, "The Lowell Observatory in Mexico," Popular Astronomy, no. 39. 1896-1897 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: "An Ascent of Popocatepetl," Appalachia, vol. 8, no. 3. July 1897 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: trip to summit of Orizaba. April 1897 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: Miss Annie Peck and mountain climbing. 1896-1897 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: Mountain heights. 1896-1897 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: Miscelaneous articles. 1896-1897 (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: Miscellaneous photographs. 1896-1897 (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - Lowell Observatory in Mexico: Mexican observatories. 1896-1897 (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - Lowell Observatory: scrapbook. (Box 21a)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Early Arizona articles, notes on photos & slides. 1894-1906 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Earthquakes in Flagstaff and San Francisco. 1903, 1906 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Miscellaneous material (personal & social). 1894-1906 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Miscellaneous material (descriptive). 1897 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Addresses (chiefly astronomical). 1905-1906 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Elks club, Flagstaff Lodge no. 499. 1894-1906 (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Northern Arizona Normal School, catalogs. 1904-1906 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Northern Arizona Normal School (A.E.D.'s notes, subject outlines, etc. for classwork). 1904-1906 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Northern Arizona Normal School (President A.N. Taylor's talks). 1905-1906 (Box 22, Folder 9)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Examination for Assistant Astronomer, U.S. Naval Observatory. No Date (Box 22, Folder 10)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: University of California, Berkeley, summer school (A.E.D's notes). 1905 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Correspondence (Mother). 1894-1906 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Correspondence (Family, relatives). 1894-1906 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Correspondence (general). 1894-1904 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Correspondence (general). 1905-1906 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Correspondence (with Flagstaff friends after leaving). (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Photographs (A.E.D.). 1894-1906 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Photographs (friends, social gatherings). 1894-1906 (Box 23, Folder 7)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: personal bills. 1899-1902 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: personal accounts and notes. 1894-1901 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Black Rock Gold and Copper Mining Co. 1901-1905 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Merchants Mining Co., Hawks Estate, and Henderson Estate. 1902-1912 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Excelsior Gold & Copper Mining Co. (correspondence). 1906-1910 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Excelsior Gold & Copper Mining Co. (correspondence). 1911-1929 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Excelsior Gold & Copper Mining Co. (legal & official papers). 1894-1906 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Excelsior Gold & Copper Mining Co. (accounts). 1894-1906 (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Manganese Mining Property, San Diego County, California. 1903-1918 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Property in Williams, AZ. 1894-1906 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Property in Flagstaff, AZ. 1894-1906 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Probate Judge Papers, I. 1902-1906 (Box 24, Folder 12)
  - Flagstaff, AZ: Probate Judge Papers, II. 1901 (Box 24, Folder 13)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): Montezuma's well, Soda Springs, Red Rock Country. 1896 (Box 25, Folder 1)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): Agassiz Peak (photographs). August 1898 (Box 25, Folder 2)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): Washington, GA, for eclipse. May 1900 (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): Trip to Lava Beds and Sunset Crater (photographs, notes, drawings). August 1900 (Box 25, Folder 4)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): "Forest trip" with Fred Breen and Al Doyle. August 1901 (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): Kanab, Fredonia, Lee's Ferry. November-December 1901 (Box 25, Folder 6)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): Colorado River Trip. February-March 1902 (Box 25, Folder 7)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): A.W. Barber trip to San Francisco Peaks. 1902 (Box 25, Folder 8)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (trips): various. 1895-1903 (Box 25a, Folder 9)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs). 1894-1906 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs): Flagstaff surroundings. 1894-1906 (Box 26, Folder 2)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs): San Francisco Peaks and views from. 1894-1906 (Box 26, Folder 3)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs): Walnut Canyon. 1894-1906 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs): Grand Canyon and John Hance. 1896 (Box 26, Folder 5)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs): Snake Dane at Oraibi. 1898 (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Flagstaff, AZ (photographs): Other towns. 1902-1904 (Box 26, Folder 7)
- Series III: University of Arizona, 1904-1962
  These boxes focus on the period from Dr. Douglass's arrival at the University in 1906 to 1937/38, when he became Director of the newly-established Laboratory of Tree Ring Research and relinquished the active headship of Steward Observatory to Dr. Edwin Carpenter. During these years he was teacher, head of the Astronomy Department, acting President, Dean of the College of Letters, Arts and Sciences, and Director of Steward Observatory.